So today is September 13th and the past
week has been insane. We saw this tweet
on September 8th from Jacob Coxin that
said, "I resigned from Enthropic today.
I spent the last three years doing
pre-training research at both OpenAI and
Enthropic. Neither company is acting
responsibly. They are racing straight to
self-improving super intelligence and
they're gambling with our lives." Now, I
have really never seen a tweet go this
viral this fast. It was like every 10
minutes it was gaining like 10 million
views. It was nuts and he talked a lot
more about why he thought this is the
case. About an hour and a half later, we
see this quote tweet on the same day
from Evan Hubinger, who as you can see
here is the alignment science lead at
Enthropic. Evan was also previously at
OpenAI. And what he says is, "Jacob is
correct. We really do earnestly believe
that AI could kill all humans with an
exclamation mark. I personally think it
is greater than a 10% chance within the
next decade. I believe Enthropic is
trying its best, but we do not yet have
a plan to solve alignment for super
intelligence and are not clearly on
track to." Now, Daario did post this
article yesterday, and it seemed like it
was in response to all this stuff that
we've been seeing on Twitter this whole
week. So, before I sort of dive into
this, I wanted to talk about what
actually happened here because a lot of
people think this is a little fishy. So,
this tweet by Dylan was really
interesting. This story is fascinating
and is easily one of the most important
things happening at the intersection of
AI and politics right now. It's critical
that everyone understands the situation
because this is just the beginning of
the AI info wars. So, Jacob Coxin, the
guy that posted that original tweet, was
a relatively unknown AI researcher and
gave the Wall Street Journal an
exclusive story about his resignation
from Anthropic and his concerns. 20
minutes after that story dropped, that's
when Jacob posted that tweet on X that
went viral. And when Ilia actually made
his resignation tweet from OpenAI, it
didn't get nearly as much attention.
Now, obviously, that was multiple years
ago and AI has since exploded, but still
people were looking at that like, hm,
you know, 150 million views and it's
already more than that. Interesting. It
was obviously a very bold statement
though, but Jacob Coxin's ex account had
no prior posting activity and was
immediately reposted and boosted by a
ton of people. Bernie Sanders was in
here talking about his legislation to
ban super intelligence and pause AI
development, and so was JB Pritsker. As
you can see here, many major Democratic
politicians are now using Jacob's expost
to fearmonger the public into voting to
regulate AI. I'm not trying to turn this
into a political debate. I'm just trying
to show you guys the story of what's
actually happening and what we should be
thinking about. Elon then pointed out
that none of that felt organic and Jacob
decided to take a shot at him for firing
some exai researchers. You can see right
here the little interchange between Elon
and Jacob. And here's just another one
about Jacob's previous sort of personal
brand. No prior tweets available, no
previous replies, just joined in January
2026, and just got verified in August.
And that means on X. Now, I'm not in
here trying to devalidate what Jacob
said, and I don't think that's what
people are trying to do. They're just
saying that the fact that he now has
almost 300,000 subscribers or sorry
followers in that short amount of time
is interesting. And then CNN brought him
on to talk about this and talk about
what happened. And he basically said
that, you know, hey, you know, I decided
to leave. I wanted to voice my opinion.
I didn't think it would go this viral. I
wrote out the Twitter thread. I had some
friends look at it and, you know, wanted
them to repost it to sort of, you know,
get it more exposure, which totally
makes sense. But people are saying that
how many organic impressions it got is
just like not possible without some sort
of planning and you know strategy which
I think is totally fair. Then on
September 10th, so 2 days after that
original tweet from Jacob, Enthropic
dropped this report on basically AI
misuse and this goes over seven harm
areas like cyber operations, influence
operations, surveillance, scams, fraud,
things like that. What stood out to me
here was that AI is doing more of the
actual hacking. So, you know, attackers
are using these agents to execute cyber
operations. We're seeing a lot more AI
scams. There was one particular
operation with a dating app where they
used like 5,000 AI personas to converse
with over, you know, tens of thousands
of people, but saying that, you know,
that was humans on the back end. And
there were some major allegations about
competing labs. Anthropic attributes
over 151 million exchanges to Alibaba's
unauthorized model training campaign and
alleges Moonshot and Deepseek secretly
routing customers to Claude when they're
saying, "Hey, you know, use our new
Deepseek model or our new Kimmy model or
whatever, and they're actually just
sending people to Claude on the back
end." But now, here's what I wanted to
spend a little more time on, which was
Daario's essay that he wrote. And I
think that this is very well written.
He's put out a lot of other thought
leadership like this in the past, and
whether you like him or not, I think he
brings up some really good points. So,
I'll link this in the description if you
want to check it out, but I'm not going
to be able to read this whole thing, but
I'll just call out some of the things
that I thought were interesting. So,
Dario has worked in AI for the last 12
years because he believes it will
dramatically raise the quality of human
life. But like many technologies before
it, AI brings risks. And because it is
such a powerful technology, these risks
are very serious. And this is the line
that I think is the most important,
which is basically about the incentives
right here. This is a race to the bottom
spurred by commercial incentives. And
that can make these risks more acute.
Now essentially what that means is that
everyone is incentivized to win.
Everyone wants to get out the best new
model with the best new benchmarks and
they want to move fast and you know the
US wants to beat China and China wants
to be the US and things like that and
that's what creates the race to the
bottom where people are trying to find
shortcuts to get things out quicker
because if you spend an extra week
training or testing your model where
someone else might get one out before
you and then they are kind of like
exploding on X and YouTube and then your
model gets overshadowed because you
spent that extra time trying to you know
make it better or make it safer even. So
he's basically talking about how do we
actually create where is it a race to
the top? How do we flip those
incentives? And it's basically right
here. Let me just read this whole
paragraph. So along with my co-founders
and employees, I have grappled with this
duality of risk and benefit since the
beginning of entropic. Not building the
technology deprivives humanity of
benefits or simply places AI in the
hands of authoritarian powers while
building it too fast is reckless. So we
have sought a middle way which is to
show that it's possible to build
carefully and succeed commercially and
to make safety something on which AI
companies compete. In other words,
create a race to the top. So it's not
just that companies are moving really
fast and building the best models. It's
that they're moving fast, building the
best models, but making sure that all of
these models are safe and they're
competing on who has the safest models
and the best governance standards and
things like that. We've always devoted a
substantial fraction of our efforts to
studying, addressing, and informing the
public about these AI risks, as well as
advocating for well-considered
regulation of AI. Even when this gets us
accused of hype, you know, dumerism or
what do they call it? Fear-mongering or
regulatory capture. We have tried to
prioritize caution over speed and
prudence over profit. Whether you
believe that or not, this is something
that we do need all of these major labs
to be thinking of. There were two main
things that kind of inspired this. You
know, he's talked about this in the
past. Both Sam Alman and Daario have
come out and said, "Hey, we need to slow
this down. We need to sort of have
everyone work together a little bit
better." But then they just kind of kept
building. But it was good for them to at
least raise that, right? Because a lot
of people did start talking about it.
But anyways, his first concern is how
fast things are moving. No one can deny
how much better this stuff is getting.
And I think it's really important that
we all as a community start raising a
ton of awareness for this stuff because
how can you have a spectrum so wide that
the leaders are putting out pieces like
this? The US government is taking away
models. And then you got the other side
where people don't even know that Claude
is a model. They only have heard of
Chhat GBT or they only use C-pilot at
work and they have no true idea of
what's actually possible. And then the
second one was the OpenAI hugging face
incident which I'm not going to dive
into today. But basically what happened
was a swarm of agents were trying to
achieve a goal. They were running into
these roadblocks and they ended up
attacking things that were unrelated. I
shouldn't have said things. I should
have said targets. They were attacking
targets that were unrelated and they
were escaping the environment they were
put in and hacking into the greater in
order to sort of like beat the benchmark
or beat the test that it was being put
up against. Anyways, he comes down here
to propose a three-step plan with the
goal of pacing the frontier, which is
embedded evaluators, meaning that each
Frontier AI company commits to giving
ongoing employee-like access to a team
of embedded third-party evaluators whose
role is to verify adherence to safety
practices and commitments and things
like that to help make sure that people
are actually doing that race to the top
rather than the race to the bottom. We
also have democratic coordination and
global coordination and these are going
to be where it gets really really
important because like I said it can't
just be that open AAI and anthropic and
maybe you know Google are working
together. It has to be the whole world
is working together. He calls out China
right here and says you know it will
require cooperation with China the
country with by far the most advanced AI
capabilities. We must not be naive here.
The geopolitical stakes are so high that
there will likely be stark limits on
what can be achieved especially at
first. If we greatly restrain our AI
capabilities and the belief that China
will do the same and then China defects,
AI could be so powerful that such a
defection could lead to their
geopolitical dominance. He ends off this
whole article by saying, "The measures I
propose to advance the frontier at a
safe pace will not be easy." And I agree
with that, but I believe we owe it to
humanity to try. And I agree with that,
of course. And then I actually just saw
this tweet where Trump reacts to all of
these, you know, recent concerning
reports that I've just discussed with
you guys. And his answer was basically,
"We're leading China in AI. We're the
most sophisticated country in the world
and I want to keep it that way because
whoever wins AI wins. And I mean I think
that this part of his statement is true.
But I think that this statement is also
why the whole world is in this race to
the bottom that Daario has mentioned in
his essay because we really never have
seen a technology this powerful that is
evolving this quickly. Now going back to
Evans tweet putting a number to this is
really interesting. Greater than 10% in
the next decade. I would love to pick
his brain a little bit more on what he
actually thinks that will look like to
play out. Anyways guys, I don't have the
answer. I think that it's really
important that we're staying as close to
the stuff as possible because
realistically,
no one knows exactly what's going to
happen. I think we all have some sort of
responsibility here. I don't think that
our responsibility is to, you know, put
out this sort of piece like Daario and
coordinate with the governments.
Obviously, that's not in our hands. But
what is in our control is raising
awareness and talking about this kind of
stuff and being safe with our data and
implementing it right for clients. And I
think one of the most important things
that you can do is send this article
around. Send these tweets around. If you
know people that you know are executives
at big companies, if you know people
that aren't listening or talking about
AI at all, just start sending this stuff
around and just start bringing up the
conversations a little bit. But like I
said, I think one of the first steps is
how do we shorten this gap? You know,
that spectrum I talked about at the
beginning. How do we bring it all into,
you know, sort of more of a gap like
this rather than having the gap be so so
wide? And I think that is something that
I can try my best to help do. And I
think that's something that everyone
that's listening to this can do by, like
I said, just sharing out this kind of
content and sharing articles like this
and just talking about it. But anyways
guys, I hope that this one was
interesting. I hope you learned
something new. And if you did, please
give it a like. It helps me out a ton.
I'll see you guys in the next one.
Thanks everyone.